

Augusto Fernandes Vellozo

possui graduação em Ciência da Computação pela Universidade Estadual de Campinas (1989), doutorado em Ciência da Computação pela Universidade de São Paulo (2007) e pós-doutorado em bioinformática na Université Lyon I (2007-2010). Tem experiência na área de Ciência da Computação, com ênfase em Teoria da Computação, atuando principalmente nos seguintes temas: alinhamneto de sequências, biologia computacional, programação dinâmica, alinhamento com rearranjos, redes metabólicas, motifs e bioinformática.

(Texto informado pelo autor)

Última atualização em 08/03/2010

Endereço para acessar este CV: http://lattes.cnpq.br/2024974104338199

Dados Pessoais

Nome Augusto Fernandes Vellozo

Filiação Eustáquio Fernandes Vellozo e Ignêz Dacal Vellozo

Nascimento 12/04/1967 - Avaré/SP - Brasil

Carteira de 16187494 SSP - SP - 10/09/1981

Identidade

CPF 07430913881

Endereço residencial 10 rue Paul Cambon

- Villeurbanne 69100, - França

Telefone: 33 426766582

Endereço Universite Claude Bernarde Lyon I

profissional 43 bd du 11 novembre 1918 - Bât. Grégor Mendel

- Villeurbanne 69622, - França

Endereço eletrônico

e-mail para contato: augustovmail-cnpq@yahoo.com.br

e-mail alternativo : avellozo@gmail.com

Formação Acadêmica/Titulação

2009 Pós-Doutorado.

Universite Claude Bernarde Lyon I, LYON I, Lyon, França

2008 - 2009 Pós-Doutorado.

Institut National des Sciences Appliquees de Lyon, INSAL*, Lyon, França

2007 - 2008 Pós-Doutorado.

Universite Claude Bernarde Lyon I, LYON I, Lyon, França

2001 - 2007 Doutorado em Ciencia da Computação.

Universidade de São Paulo, USP, Sao Paulo, Brasil

Título: Alinhamento de seqüências com rearranjos, Ano de obtenção: 2007

Orientador: Alair Pereira do Lago

Bolsista do(a): Coordenação de Aperfeiçoamento de Pessoal de Nível Superior

1997 - 1998 Especialização em Informática e Sistemas de Informação.

Universidade de Sorocaba, UNISO, Sorocaba, Brasil

Título: Banco de dados orientado a objetos

1995 - 1996 Especialização em Administração de marketing. Universidade de Sorocaba, UNISO, Sorocaba, Brasil Título: Marketing em pequenas empresas

1985 - 1989 Graduação em Ciência da Computação.

Universidade Estadual de Campinas, UNICAMP, Campinas, Brasil

Atuação profissional

1. Universite Claude Bernarde Lyon I - LYON I

Vínculo institucional

2009 - Atual Vínculo: Celetista formal , Enquadramento funcional: Pós-doutorado , Carga horária: 40, Regime: Dedicação Exclusiva

2007 - 2008 Vínculo: Celetista formal , Enquadramento funcional: Pós-doutorado , Carga horária: 40, Regime: Dedicação Exclusiva

Atividades

07/2009 - Atual Projetos de pesquisa, LBBE - UMR CNRS 5558 Laboratoire de Biométrie et Biologie évolutive

Participação em projetos:

MetNet - Systems level analysis of the Pea Aphid , NEMO - Network Motifs

2. Institut National des Sciences Appliquees de Lyon - INSAL*

Vínculo institucional

2008 - 2009 Vínculo: Celetista formal , Enquadramento funcional: Pós-doutorado , Carga horária: 40, Regime: Dedicação Exclusiva

Atividades

07/2008 - 07/2009 Projetos de pesquisa, Biologie Fonctionnelle Insectes et Interactions - BF2I

Participação em projetos: MetNet - Systems level analysis of the Pea Aphid

3. Universidade de São Paulo - USP

Vínculo institucional

2004 - 2007 Vínculo: Outro (Aluno) , Enquadramento funcional: Aluno Doutorado

Atividades

2006 - 2007 Projetos de pesquisa, Instituto de Matemática e Estatística, Departamento de Ciência da Computação

Participação em projetos:

Computational Biology, Algorithmics, Combinatorial Optimization

2004 - 2007 Projetos de pesquisa, Instituto de Matemática e Estatística, Departamento de Ciência da Computação

Participação em projetos: Algorithmic Questions on Molecular Biology

4. Instituto Brasileiro de Tecnologia Avançada - IBTA

Vínculo institucional

2002 - 2003 Vínculo: Celetista, Enquadramento funcional: Professor titular II, Carga horária: 12, Regime: Parcial

Atividades

02/2002 - 06/2003 Graduação, Administração de redes

Disciplinas Ministradas:

Programção orientada a objetos, Fundamentos de software

02/2002 - 06/2003 Graduação, Banco de Dados

Disciplinas Ministradas:

Fundamentos de software, Programação orientada a objetos

5. Universo OnLine Ltda. - UOL

Vínculo institucional

2000 - 2004 Vínculo: Celetista, Enquadramento funcional: Analista programador, Carga horária: 40, Regime: Integral

Atividades

04/2000 - 01/2004 Serviço Técnico Especializado, Departamento de desenvolvimento de software

Especificação:

Desenvolvimento de software

6. Banco Bradesco - BRADESCO

Vínculo institucional

1999 - 2000 Vínculo: Colaborador , Enquadramento funcional: Analista programador , Carga horária: 40, Regime: Dedicação Exclusiva

7. Banco Finasa - FINASA

Vínculo institucional

1997 - 1999 Vínculo: Celetista , Enquadramento funcional: Analista programador , Carga horária: 40, Regime: Dedicação Exclusiva

8. Vellozo Informática - VELLOZO

Vínculo institucional

1995 - 1997 Vínculo: Proprietário , Enquadramento funcional: Analista programador , Carga horária: 40, Regime: Dedicação Exclusiva

9. ABR Sistemas - ABR

Vínculo institucional

1992 - 1995 Vínculo: Sócio, Enquadramento funcional: Diretor, Carga horária: 40, Regime: Dedicação Exclusiva

10. Quantum Computadores - QUANTUM

Vínculo institucional

1989 - 1991

Vínculo: Celetista , Enquadramento funcional: Analista programador , Carga horária: 40, Regime: Dedicação Exclusiva

Projetos

2009 - 2010 MetNet - Systems level analysis of the Pea Aphid

Descrição: From a metabolic perspective, an animal comprises a set of metabolic compartments (including organs) connected by the inter-compartment transfer of metabolites. We seek to construct and analyse multicompartment models of metabolism, by transforming a single global metabolic network into a set of compartment networks of overlapping composition using flux balance analysis. In parallel, we will develop and apply two computational approaches for network analysis: an exploration of metabolic network motifs, and elementary modes to characterize and compare networks. Large inter-compartment metabolic differences facilitating model development will be achieved in our system comprising two distinct genomes within a single animal: the pea aphid Acyrthosiphon pisum and its symbiotic bacteria Buchnera housed in a special organ, the bacteriome. The first model comprises two compartments, describing how the insect and bacterial networks mediate the transformation of precisely known diet components to yield biomass production (and waste); and subsequent models are of increasing complexity, involving the subdivision of the insect network into overlapping, but distinct, networks of the contributing compartments/organs. Model construction will be informed by empirical data collected on the aphid transcriptome, Buchnera proteome and embryo nutrient budgets within this project, and the model outputs will be validated against whole-insect metabolic and nutritional datasets obtained previously from the investigators' labs. Algorithms and models developed in this project will be maintained in a central Repository linked to pre-existing databases, suitable for data-sharing within the project and dissemination to the wider community. The outputs will include metabolic network data for a range of insects with well-developed genomic resources.

Situação: Em Andamento Natureza: Pesquisa

Integrantes: Augusto Fernandes Vellozo; Marie France Sagot (Responsável)

Financiador(es): Agence Nationale de la Recherche-ANR

2009 - 2010 NEMO - Network Motifs

Descrição: The project is organized into 5 tasks: 1. Definition and enumeration of network motifs 2. Realistic random graph models for biological networks 3. Assessing motif exceptionality 4. Network comparison 5. From network motifs to data integration

Situação: Em Andamento Natureza: Pesquisa

Integrantes: Augusto Fernandes Vellozo; Marie France Sagot (Responsável)

Financiador(es):

2008 - 2009 MetNet - Systems level analysis of the Pea Aphid

Descrição: From a metabolic perspective, an animal comprises a set of metabolic compartments (including organs) connected by the inter-compartment transfer of metabolites. We seek to construct and analyse multicompartment models of metabolism, by transforming a single global metabolic network into a set of compartment networks of overlapping composition using flux balance analysis. In parallel, we will develop and apply two computational approaches for network analysis: an exploration of metabolic network motifs, and elementary modes to characterize and compare networks. Large inter-compartment metabolic differences facilitating model development will be achieved in our system comprising two distinct genomes within a single animal: the pea aphid Acyrthosiphon pisum and its symbiotic bacteria Buchnera housed in a special organ, the bacteriome. The first model comprises two compartments, describing how the insect and bacterial networks mediate the transformation of precisely known diet components to yield biomass production (and waste); and subsequent models are of increasing complexity, involving the subdivision of the insect network into overlapping, but distinct, networks of the contributing compartments/organs. Model construction will be informed by empirical data collected on the aphid transcriptome, Buchnera proteome and embryo nutrient budgets within this project, and the model outputs will be validated against whole-insect metabolic and nutritional datasets obtained previously from the investigators' labs. Algorithms and models developed in this project will be maintained in a central Repository linked to pre-existing databases, suitable for data-sharing within the project and dissemination to the wider community. The outputs will include metabolic network data for a range of insects with well-developed genomic resources.

Situação: Concluído Natureza: Pesquisa

Integrantes: Augusto Fernandes Vellozo; Marie France Sagot (Responsável)

Financiador(es): Agence Nationale de la Recherche-ANR

2006 - 2007 Computational Biology, Algorithmics, Combinatorial Optimization

Descrição: The research proposed will focus mainly on computational biology. The technological advances in biological related areas of recent years has allowed a huge amount of information to be produced. It is one of the main current challenges for biologists to be able to extract knowledge from all this data, and a challenge also for the computer scientists and mathematicians to participate with the biologists in this process. The analysis of this data involves, among many other issues, the formalization of problems and the search for efficient algorithms to solve them. This is a continuous process in the sense that the solutions produced by the algorithms will usually lead to new research that has for objective refining the models, and will therefore result in new problems and/or the development of increasingly more sophisticated algorithms. The main goal of the association between the HELIX and USP teams is to work on such types of questions: the formalization of problems coming from biology and the search for efficient algorithms to solve these problems. Situação: Concluído Natureza: Pesquisa

Alunos envolvidos: Graduação (0); Especialização (0); Mestrado acadêmico (0); Mestrado profissionalizante (0); Doutorado (2);

Integrantes: Augusto Fernandes Vellozo; Yoshiko Wakabayashi (Responsável) Financiador(es): Fundação de Amparo à Pesquisa do Estado de São Paulo-FAPESP

2004 - 2005 Algorithmic Questions on Molecular Biology

Descrição: The research proposed here will mainly focus on computational biology. The technological advances in biology related areas allowed a huge amount of information to be extracted. It is one of the main current challenges for biologists to be able to extract knowledge from all this data and a challenge also for the computer scientists to help the biologists in this process. The analysis of this data involves, among many other issues, the formalization of problems and the search for efficient algorithms to solve these problems. This is a continous process in the sense that the solutions produced by the algorithms will usually lead a refinement of the models and problem formulations, and will therefore require new algorithms. The main goal of this project is to work on these type of questions: the formalization fo problems coming from biology and the search for efficient algorithms for these problems. http://www.ime.usp.br/~cris/inria/

Situação: Concluído Natureza: Pesquisa

Alunos envolvidos: Graduação (2); Especialização (0); Mestrado acadêmico (0); Mestrado profissionalizante (2); Doutorado (2);

Integrantes: Augusto Fernandes Vellozo; Carlos Eduardo Ferreira (Responsável) Financiador(es): Fundação de Amparo à Pesquisa do Estado de São Paulo-FAPESP

Áreas de atuação

- 1. Biologia Computacional
- 2. Teoria da Computação
- 3. Sistemas de Computação
- 4. Metodologia e Técnicas da Computação

Idiomas

Inglês Compreende Razoavelmente , Fala Razoavelmente, Escreve Razoavelmente, Lê Bem

Francês Compreende Bem , Fala Razoavelmente, Escreve Razoavelmente, Lê Bem

Português Compreende Bem , Fala Bem, Escreve Bem, Lê Bem

Produção em C, T& A

Produção bibliográfica

Artigos completos publicados em periódicos

 doi> The International Aphid Genomics Consortium, Augusto Vellozo
 Genome Sequence of the Pea Aphid Acyrthosiphon pisum. PLoS Biology., v.8, p.e1000313 - , 2010.
 Referências adicionais: Inglês. Meio de divulgação: Meio digital, Home page: [http://dx.doi.org/10.1371%2Fjournal.pbio.1000313]
 [doi:10.1371/journal.pbio.1000313]

Trabalhos publicados em anais de eventos (completo)

Augusto F. Vellozo, carlos e r alves, Alair Pereira do Lago
 Alignment with non-overlapping inversions in {\$O(n^ 3)\$}-time ln: WABI, 2006, Zurique.
 Algorithms in Bioinformatics. Berlin / Heidelberg: Springer, 2006. v.4175. p.186 - 196
 Referências adicionais: Suiça/Inglês. Meio de divulgação: Vários, Home page: [http://www.springerlink.com/content/w1gw8u371006g603/]

Trabalhos publicados em anais de eventos (resumo expandido)

doi> carlos e r alves, Alair Pereira do Lago, Augusto F. Vellozo
 Alignment with non-overlapping inversions in {\$O(n^ 3\logn)\$}-time ln: GRACO, 2005, Angra dos Reis.
 Electronic Notes in Discrete Mathematics - Proceedings of GRACO2005. Amsterdam: Elsevier, 2005. v.19. p.365 - 371
 Referências adicionais: Holanda/Inglês. Meio de divulgação: Vários, Home page: [http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/b75gv-4g8mt0t-1p/2/15ca35c3828cd2c20967326055dbf2f7]

Produção Técnica

Softwares sem registro ou patente

 Augusto Vellozo, Stefano Colella Cycads - Cyc Annotation Database system, 2009

Demais produções técnicas

Augusto Vellozo, Stefano Colella
 AcypiCyc - Acyrthosiphon pisum Cyc database, 2009. (Outra produção técnica)

Referências adicionais: França/Inglés. Meio de divulgação: Meio digital http://acypicyc.cycadsys.org http://acypicyc.cycadsys.org Abstract: The AcypiCyc database has been generated at the Université de Lyon in a collaboration between the UMR203 INRA-INSA de Lyon, Biologie fonctionelle des insectes et interactions (BF2) and the Baobab team at UMR5558 LBBE CNRS-UCBL1; both groups are member of the INRIA Bamboo team-project. The database is hosted at the Pôle Rhône-Alpes de Bioinformatique (PRABI). We are working on a version that includes KAAS, PRIAM, BLAST2GO and PhylomeDB annotations. We will add more annotations soon. At present, you will be able to compare \text{\text{\text{bill}} Acyrthosiphon pisum} metabolism to \text{\text{\text{emph}{Buchnera aphidicola}} APS REVISED (generated in Lyon inside the SymbioCyc database).

Eventos

Participação em eventos

- Apresentação de Poster / Painel no(a) 6th ISS Congress., 2009. (Congresso)
 AcypiCyc (Acyrthosiphon pisum Cyc database): a model database to visualize and study the metabolic network underlying the pea aphid-Buchnera symbiosis.
- Apresentação de Poster / Painel no(a) Réseau Français de Biologie Adaptative des Pucerons, 2009. (Simpósio)
 AcypiCyc (Acyrthosiphon pisum Cyc database) and CycADS (Cyc Annotation Database System): moving from genome sequence
 annotation to metabolic network analyses..
- Apresentação de Poster / Painel no(a) 8th International Symposium on Aphids, 2009. (Simpósio)
 AcypiCyc (Acyrthosiphon pisum Cyc database) and CycADS (Cyc Annotation Database System): moving from genome sequence
 annotation to metabolic network analyses..
- 4. Apresentação de Poster / Painel no(a) Il Pea Aphid Genome Annotation Workshop, 2009. (Simpósio) The Acyrthosiphon pisum Cyc database (AcypiCyc) created using a novel BioCyc Annotation Database System (CycADS): a useful tool to explore and study the pea aphid metabolism..
- 5. Metabolic Pathways Analysis 2009, 2009. (Simpósio)
- 6. Apresentação de Poster / Painel no(a) Pea Aphid Genome Annotation Workshop I, 2008. (Simpósio) Annotation of metabolism genes: towards the implementation of an Acyrthosiphon pisum Cyc database (ApsCyc) to perform metabolic network analyses.
- Apresentação de Poster / Painel no(a) IPG (Integrative Post-Genomics), 2008. (Simpósio)
 Development of the Acyrthosiphon pisum Cyc database (ApsCyc): from genome sequence to metabolic network analyses.

8. BioCyc and Pathway Tools tutorial, 2008. (Oficina)

9. JOBIM, 2008. (Congresso)

Página gerada pelo Sistema Currículo Lattes em 08/03/2010 às 10:28:15.